start with two positive real numbers a
and b and draw a rectangle with width
root B plus root B and length root a
plus root a inside this rectangular
diagram we can shade two sub rectangles
like this the unshaded area in this
rectangle is then given by two < of B by
of a rectangles for a total unshaded
area of 2 * the of a * B but now we can
cut those two shaded rectangles into two
triangles each and slide those triangles
around the rectangle like this the
resulting unshaded area is now a
parallelogram we can call this angle
Thea and the side lengths are both the
of a plus b by the Pythagorean theorem
using the formula for the area of a
parallelogram we see that the unshaded
area is theun of a plus b^ 2 * the S of
theta but now in this equality we see
that the S of theta is always less than
or equal to 1 so that 2 * the S of a * B
is less than or equal to a + b or
equivalently that the of a * B is less
than or equal to a + b / 2 we get
equality if and only if s of theta
equals 1 so that the angle is 90° and a
equals B this is the arithmetic mean
geometric mean inequality